All right, welcome to the 1920s, y'all.
And that means it's time to talk about
the innovations and technologies that
contributed to the metric butt-loads of
prosperity that made this decade roar.
So, if you're ready to get them brain
cows milked, let's get to it. So, let's
start by talking about the causes of
America's fantastic economic growth and
prosperity in the '20s. And the big
honking cause for this growth was that
the US economy became more and more
focused on the mass production and
consumption of consumer goods. And that
change had three distinct causes, and
I'm in the mood to high-splain them up
for you. Okay, the first cause of this
economic change was government policy.
where I tell you that after World War I,
much of the energy of progressivism and
the heavy-handed government intervention
that came with it had essentially
petered out. And what replaced it was a
decade of conservative politics that
went right back to the laissez-faire
policies of the Gilded Age. At least
that's the kind of talk that was coming
out of their mouth-hole. In reality, the
prosperity of the 1920s was largely
facilitated by federal policies because
conservatives were more than willing to
wield their power to support and protect
big businesses and the ultra-rich. For
example, recall that one major
progressive era reform was the
ratification of the 16th Amendment,
which enacted an income tax. the height
of World War I, the wealthiest Americans
had a tax burden of almost 70%. And no,
I did not stutter. If you were making
boocoos of cash during the war, then for
every $10 you made, seven of them went
straight into the pocket of Big Daddy
Government. But, once the war was over
and politics shifted in the conservative
direction with the election of Warren G.
Harding, that top tax bracket dropped to
something like 20 to 25%. And the idea
was that if wealthy Americans had more
money, then they would invest it into
businesses, which would in turn create
more jobs for the working class, and in
that way, wealth would trickle down from
the rich to the masses. Additionally,
Harding's Secretary of Commerce and
future President Herbert Hoover further
integrated government and business
interests by championing a set of
conservative policies known as the
American Plan. Basically, Republicans
believed that labor unions hindered
prosperity, and to put a finer point on
it, were un-American. And so, the
American Plan sought to weaken the
influence of unions by incentivizing
businesses to offer their workers the
same welfare programs that unions had
previously provided, things like health
insurance and pension plans. Anyway, the
point is the prosperity of the 1920s
owed a whole lot to significant
government intervention, even though
Republicans like to say that they wanted
less government intervention. Oh, and by
the way, if you want no guys to follow
along with this video and all my videos,
check that link in the description.
Okay, the second development that helped
facilitate prosperity and the focusing
of the economy on consumer goods was new
technologies. And there are so many
examples here, but I will restrain
myself to mention only a few. First of
all, the electrification of homes was
becoming more widespread and a whole
host of consumer goods that took
advantage of electricity hit the market.
Americans could now buy vacuum cleaners
and washing machines and electric
refrigerators. And in light of all that,
businesses did not leave their customers
purchasing decisions to chance. No, it
was during the 1920s that the
advertising industry really got its big
boy pants on. And thanks to Sigmund
Freud's studies on human psychology,
advertisers learned how to promote their
products through ads that attempted to
tap into the subconscious of their
customers. Like, no longer did they
encourage you to buy this toaster
because it was better than other
toasters. Now, they messed with
Americans' brains and said, like, if you
don't have this toaster, can you even
call yourself a woman? But then, the
third development that led to this
consumeristic shift was new
manufacturing techniques, and the most
potent example here is Henry Ford's
assembly line. Now, to be clear, Ford
didn't invent the assembly line, but he
sure dang near perfected it. So, in
Ford's automobile factories, partially
built automobiles would move along a
line while workers remained stationary.
So, when the car stopped at their
station, the worker performed his or her
very specific task, and then the car
moved along to the next worker. And in
that way, a worker in Ford's assembly
line stood in one place for the entirety
of their work day, performing the same
task over and over and over again. And
while such a system created no small
amount of drudgery for his assembly line
workers, the increased efficiency,
reduced cost, and made it possible for
Ford to offer automobiles at a price
that many middle-class customers could
afford. Now, the perfection of Ford's
method owed much to his application of
Frederick Taylor's principles of
scientific management, to which I
introduced you in unit six. Okay, so
that was a very small sampling of all
the developments that made the 1920s so
prosperous, but now let's shift and
consider four effects of this economic
boom. First of all, many Americans
experienced an improved standard of
living. On the whole, the national
income for the United States rose nearly
40% in this decade, and the purchasing
power of average workers increased by
about 20%. And of course, that's just
the national average, and there were
many exceptions to that rule. Like in
general, black American workers and
immigrants were far less affected by the
wider prosperity of the nation.
Additionally, many farmers were burdened
by increasing debt since wartime
overproduction had left them with more
products to sell than there were buyers.
But then, the second effect of this
economic growth was greater personal
mobility for Americans, and a big part
of this was the widespread adoption of
the automobile. So, by the end of the
decade, Americans owned something like
80% of all automobiles worldwide. And
that's because, like I mentioned
earlier, the price of cars dropped
dramatically during the 1920s so that
middle-class Americans, not to mention a
hearty number of working-class
Americans, could afford them. And that
had a profound impact on American
society. So, with the passage of the
Federal Road Aid Act in 1916, the
federal government subsidized thousands
of miles of paved roads throughout the
country, which made travel by car much
easier. And one of the main consequences
of those developments was that wealthy
and middle-class Americans began moving
outside of urban areas into suburbs,
which fundamentally changed the
demographic makeup of the cities
themselves. And then, the third effect
of the general prosperity of the decade
was better communication systems. For
example, radio became one of the most
widespread communication technologies
over the course of the '20s, and that
led to the spread of a mass culture, of
which I shall have more to say in a
moment. But, better communication was
also facilitated by the widespread
adoption of the telephone. And although
the telephone was invented in the 19th
century, its use exploded in the 1920s
thanks to AT&T's rapid expansion of
telephone lines throughout the nation
and internationally. And finally, the
fourth effect of economic prosperity
during the '20s was the growing
influence of mass culture. And first of
all, it was the radio that was largely
responsible for this development. So, at
the beginning of the decade, radio
technology was highly niche and used by
a relatively few number of Americans.
However, by the end of the decade,
millions of Americans had radios in
their homes, and that was thanks to mass
production, which made them cheaper, and
the growing adoption of electricity in
people's homes. And so, national
networks like NBC and CBS broadcast
national radio programs to millions of
American homes, and that had the effect
of creating a mass culture. And in that
way, radio programs reduced regional
isolation and contributed to the
standardization of language and accent.
But, at the same time, this flood of
mass media provided Americans with a
greater awareness of distinct regional
cultures, as well. For example, Jack L.
Cooper was a popular black radio host
based in Chicago, and he introduced many
Americans to the black jazz and blues
artists that had become popular during
the Harlem Renaissance. But, also, the
rise of American cinema played a big
role in the spread of mass culture, as
well. By the end of the 1920s, almost
3/4 of the American population was
attending movies on a weekly basis. And
so, Hollywood, California, became the
economic center for the mass production
of films, and thanks to the rapid
multiplication of movie theaters, films
became an affordable escape for many
working and middle-class Americans. All
right, you can click here to watch my
other videos from Unit 7, or you can
click here to grab my video note guides,
which is going to help you get all the
contents of this course firmly crammed
into your brain full. And I'm glad you
came around, and I'll catch you on the
flip flop. I'm Laura Ann Tanksley.